# 大家好 今年種點這個果樹啊 在那個山上 到時候
Hi everyone! We're planting some fruit trees this year, on the hill. Then later,
# 在那個山上 到時候我們就有果子吃啦
on the hill, later, we'll have a lot of fruits.
# 順便把子孩也帶上 是吧
We're going with the kids, see?
# 下著雨 他們都要來
It's raining now, but they're still coming with us.
# 就在前面
It's right in front of us.
# 我們走過去
Let's go over there.
# 我天不怕我還地不怕
Nothing can scare me, neither thunderstorm nor earthquake!
# 看一下你頭髮
Look at your hair!
# 要不要 要不要 你們要不要吃的
You want some? You want some? Do you guys want some snacks?
# 那種很上火的這種 要不要
It's the one which is really "yeet hay". You want some?
# 一人一個
One each.
# 我要吃
I want some,
# 沙琪瑪
some sachima!
# 沙琪瑪沒拿的哦
But I didn't bring any sachima.
# 這種這個是不是
So that's what we're gonna plant, isn't it?
# 這個甚麼
What is it in fact?
# 西紅杮
Tomatoes
# 爸爸
Daddy!
# 我要沙琪瑪
I want sachima!
# 這是攝影小哥奶奶哦 快九十歲啦
This is Mr. Cameraman's grandma. She'll be ninety soon.
# 這是她買的 這個西紅杮苗 跟那個 攀蒲苗
She bought us these seedlings. There are tomato seedlings, and you know, pumpkin seedlings.
# 她買了點回來 種一下
She's bought some seedlings and we plant them today.
# 老人家就喜歡看到自己種的 種的東西
Elderly enjoys seeing their own, their own plants grow.
# 一個 一個穴位就放兩棵 (註︰穴位.....)
I'll put two, two seedlings in each hole.
# 你看 一個穴位就放兩個
Look! Two seedlings in one hole
# 它這個西紅杮容易長 這個
The tomato doesn't need too much care, I mean,
# 隨便搞點泥就可以了
some soil is all it needs.
# 這多種點
Let me plant more here.
# 這棵剩下一棵 單啦 這一棵 沒辦法
Only one remains. It's single, a single one, anyway.
# 不夠配對
I don't have one more to match it.
# 現在下雨啦 躲一下雨 在那房子裡面躲下雨
It's raining now. Let's take a shelter. Let's take a shelter inside that house.
# 你看 這個是攀蒲 現在不下雨啦 趁早把它種下去
Look! These are pumpkins. The rain has stopped. Let's get them planted as soon as possible.
# 這裡就可以種
We can just plant them here.
# 這樣就種好啦
So now it's done.
# 先把土鋤好 然後就種下去
I dig a hole first, and then put in the seedlings.
# 要兩棵一起好 比較有伴 長勢也長得比較好
I need to put them in pairs. So that they have a companion and can grow better.
# 可以 就這樣
Alright! That's it!
# 還有一棵
Here's one more.
# 這樣就種好一棵
So then one is planted.
# 就買了幾棵 一要那麼多
We've bought only a few cuz we don't need too many.
# 去年種的 種太多啦 吃都吃不完
We planted too, we planted too many last year. We just couldn't finish them.
# 全部用來餵小豬了
And all were taken to the piglets.
# 今年就種了六棵 六棵就足夠了
We've just planted six this year. Six would be enough.
# 把那果樹也種一下
Let's plant the fruit trees as well.
# 果樹到那邊去種
We plant the fruit trees over there.
# 要挖個坑
I need to dig a hole first.
# 這個太大啦 妹妹你拿不拿起起
It's too big baby. Can you really take it?
# 拿要不就 讓我來拿吧
Let, why not, let me take it if she can't?
# 好這個給 給妹妹
Alright! This is for, for baby.
# 來 胡韋汝
C'mon! Hu Weiru
# 把這個樹苗放在這裡
Put the seedling here.
# 種 種樹啦
Let's, let's plant the tree.
# 最後一個啦
It's the last one.
# 你也要來是不是 好
You wanna try too, don't you? Alright!
# 重新挖一個
I'll dig another hole.
# 我要那個
I want that one!
# 可以可以 我要這個玩沙沙
Alright, alright!
I want that one to play with the sand (soil)!
# 好 等下一起玩
Sure! We'll play together in a second!
# 別搞到手了啊
Don't hurt your hands!
# 快點 這裡還有一棵 你要就來
C'mon! Here's one more! Come here if you wanna try!
# 快點 快點去 妹妹去
C'mon! Let's go! Let's go baby!
# 嗯 就這樣踩下去啊 你們兩個 把這個土 踩結實一點啊
Um! Just step on it! You two! Step on the soil to make it firm!
# 妹妹也去 結實一點啊 去
Baby too! Make it firm, alright? Let's go!
# 別踩死啦
Don't step on the seedling!
# 這裡 這裡兩棵的
Here, here are two.
# 拔一棵來
I'll take one.
# 你不要揮這個鋤頭
Don't play with the hoe!
# 這個桃樹哦
This is a peach tree.
# 來把這個踩結 踩結實了啊
Come and step on it. Make, make it firm.
# 妹妹 你也去踩一下
Baby, would you step on it too?
# 踩
Step
# 好
Alright!
# 快點 踩
C'mon! Step on it!
# 這裡
Here!
# 你看 這棵是楊梅樹哦
Look! This is a "yangmei" (plum) tree.
# 到時候種下去的話就有楊梅吃啦
Then, when we plant it, then we can have plums later.
# 爸爸 我要跟 我也要跟他們一起玩沙子
Daddy! I wanna, I also wanna play with the sand (soil) together with them.
# 這個楊梅樹很漂亮的哦
This plum tree is really pretty!
# 這個要慢慢種
I need to do it slowly.
# 這個草先遮一下先
Let me first cover it with the grass first,
# 再加點泥土
and then put some soil.
# 可以啦
Alright!
# 這個楊梅樹
It's a plum tree.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 今天的視頻就到這裡啦 要回去啦
The video ends here. We need to go back now.
# 好像又要下雨啦
It will rain again very soon.
# 再不回去等下全部都淋都落場雞
We'll all get soaked if we stay any longer here.
# 啊 好 先回去啦
Ah! Good! Let's go back first.
# 走啦
Let's go!
# 快點 把那個衣服拿上來 (註︰不明白)
C'mon, hurry up! Take the clothes!
# 拿起來啦
Hold it!
# 有只黑狗 黑狗 黑狗在這裡
Isn't here a black dogs?
Black dog? Black dog is here.
# 不要去砸它 劉星辰
Don't throw onto the dog, Liu Xingchen!
# 等下它要咬你了
He's coming to bite you!
# 這裡有 這裡有更靚的 這裡
Here! Here's one even more beautiful! Here!
# 你看 這裡 這裡可以用來種菜的哦
Look! Here, we can plant some veggies here, you know.
# 攝影小哥奶奶很喜歡種菜
Mr. Cameraman's grandma enjoys planting veggies a lot.
# 到時候我們把它圍起來
We can fence it off later.
# 小狗就踩不到那個菜了
Then the doggies can't step on the veggies.
# 我也想要種點青菜
I wanna plant some veggies too.
# 好不好吃
Does it taste good?
# 跑到那裡去啦
Where's the dog now?
# 我要把它跑下來
I'm gonna take it back here!